A Guide to the Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Joseph Carrington Cabell Relating to the Founding of the University of Virginia
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2791, 2791-a, 2791-b
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Mrs. Raymond Orf, Bremo Recess, 1972 July 25.
Biographical/Historical Information
Joseph Carrington Cabell, 1778-1856, was an early adherent to Jefferson's party and well-traveled for his day--having completed a tour of Europe November 1802-May 1806--Cabell had opportunities to serve in the administrations of Presidents Madison and Monroe. He declined even to run for a congressional seat, preferring Richmond to Washington. He served for decades in the Virginia General Assembly not because he was incapable of attaining a higher station, but because his service there well-positioned him to advance his two great interests, the University of Virginia and the James River & Kanawha Canal.
Thomas Jefferson recruited Cabell's aid in the earliest stages of planning for the University of Virginia. Jefferson first raised the issue with his friend in a letter of 5 January 1815, and Cabell thereafter served as the University's most faithful advocate in the state legislature. He was the prime mover first behind the incorporation of Central College in 1817 and second behind the selection of Central College as the official state university in 1819. In that year, Cabell joined Jefferson, his best friend John Hartwell Cocke, and several other of the Commonwealth's most distinguished citizens on the University's first Board of Visitors. When Cabell's energy faded and he considered resigning his post in the state legislature, Jefferson begged his friend in the strongest possible terms not to abandon his post as the institution's most capable friend in Richmond. "Nature will not give you a second life wherein to atone for the omissions of this. Pray then, dear and very dear sir, do not think of deserting us," he pined in January 1821. Cabell found some hidden reserve of energy and served the University of Virginia longer than any of its original founders, as a Board member until his death in 1856 and as a member of the General Assembly until 1835.
In addition to his remarkable contributions to the University, Cabell spearheaded the drive for internal improvements in the state of Virginia. He doggedly pursued his goal of connecting the James and Kanawha Rivers, thereby linking the Chesapeake watershed and the Mississippi River, and demonstrated perseverance and political acumen that even his opponents admired. Editor of the Richmond Whig, John Hampden Pleasants, marveled in 1842 at Cabell's ability to keep the project afloat despite the disapprobation of a majority of his fellow citizens. "To keep this majority passive, and not merely passive, but to impel them into active co-operation," he wrote, "argues a great knowledge of mankind, and a great talent for influencing them."
Cabell died at his Nelson County estate, "Edgewood," in February of 1856, survived by his wife of forty-nine years, Mary Walker Carter Cabell. Cabell left no children to mourn his passing, but the Faculty and Visitors of the University each passed resolutions honoring him. His grateful successors on the Board further commemorated his sacrifices on their behalf by naming the University's new academic center Cabell Hall in 1895.
Scope and Content
This collection consists primarily of Joseph Carrington Cabell's letters to Thomas Jefferson, 1810-1826, concerning the founding of the University of Virginia; the collection also includes Cabell's copies of the University of Virginia Board of Visitors' minutes and his memoranda concerning passages of Jefferson correspondence omitted from Nathaniel Francis Cabell's Early history of the University of Virginia, as contained in the letters of Thomas Jefferson and Joseph C. Cabell, hitherto unpublished (Richmond, Va.: J. W. Randolph, 1856.)
Contents List
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1810 July 23, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 2-5. (Box-folder 1:1)
  Unwillingness to enter into an agreement with Judge Cooper regarding collection of minerals. His knowledge only that of an amateur. His collection lent to William and Mary and to [Louis H.?] Girardin.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1813 January 12., ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 6. (Box-folder 1:2)
  Defense of T. J.'s rights against the petition of the Rivanna Company. References to [Philip P.?] Barbour and [Chapman] Johnson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1813 February 17., ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 7-8. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Services by Cabell, [P. P.?] Barbour, and [Chapman] Johnson in the Virginia legislature in defense of T. J.'s rights against the bill petitioned by the Rivanna Company. Action in the Senate and House of Delegates. Use of T. J.'s canal by the company and exemption of T. J.'s and his customer's produce from tools were involved.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Williamsburg, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1813 November 29., ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 10-12. (Box-folder 1:4)
  Bill concerning T. J. and the Rivanna River Co. will pass the Virginia Assembly. Disagrees with T. J. on the length of the charter. Prefers Jean Baptiste Say's book on political economy to Adam Smith's.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1813 December 8, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 12-13. (Box-folder 1:5)
  Books forwarded through General Moore. Reelection of Governor Barbour expected despite discontent throughout the state. Consultation with Charles Everett and Jesse W. Garth relative to the petition of the Rivanna River Co.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1814 January 23, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 16-18. (Box-folder 1:6)
  Expresses limited approval of a state banking system. Voted for chartering Bank of Virginia. Restriction of the residence of a member of the House of Representatives to the district from which he was elected. Bill respecting the Rivanna River Company. Reasons for the division of state into wards.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1814 February 5, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 21-23. (Box-folder 1:7)
  Assembly's action on residence requirements for Congressmen. Passage of the Rivanna River Company bill in form agreed upon by T. J. and [Dabney] Minor. Bill to charter bank at Wheeling.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Carysbrook, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1814 March 6, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 24. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Return of T. J.'s letters on banking and finance which have been shown to William C. Rives, [John?] Tucker, Thomas Ritchie, and [John H.] Cocke.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1814 September 17, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 24-27. (Box-folder 1:9)
  Preparations for defense of Richmond against the British. Lack of money in treasury at Washington and Richmond. Loans from Bank of Virginia and from the Farmers' Bank to the state. Stopping of specie payment in these banks. Suggests Colonel Nicholas as next governor.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1814 October 19, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 32. (Box-folder 1:10)
  Issuing of state certificates to bolster public credit.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1814 December 27, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 32-35. (Box-folder 1:11)
  Tracy's work on political economy. Possible solutions of the problems of financing the state government: loan from the Farmer's Bank; issuance of treasury notes by the state; or a private loan by citizens. Thomas Mann Randolph's petition to open the falls near Milton and charge tolls on traffic conflicts with the Rivanna River Charter. References to Charles Yancey and William Wood.
- Albemarle Academy, Central College, Visitor's Minutes. 1814-1826., AD. #2791 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Minutes of the Trustees of Albemarle Academy 1814-1817, the Board of Visitors of Central College 1817-1819, and the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia 1819-1826. 1817-1826, AD. MS. Vol. 65 pp., 6 pp., 2 pp. #2791-a (Box-folder 1:13)
  Copies of the minutes belonging to Joseph Carrington Cabell. Some of the notes date from 1814, with the minutes of the Trustees of Albemarle Academy. The notes for 1826 March 4 and 5 (2 pp.) have interlineations in T. J.'s hand. (See "Bibliography of Unprinted Official Records" in sixth Annual Report of the Archivist, Univ. of Va., 1935-36).
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1815 March 5, ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 38-41. (Box-folder 1:14)
  Petition regarding the setting up of an academy in Albemarle County; possible effect on the College of William and Mary. Hopes it will induce such men as Jean Baptiste Say to reside in Virginia. Disposition of his slaves from Corotoman taken by the British. References to Dr. [Charles?] Carr, Peter Carr, Admiral Cockburn, John A. Smith, Destutt de Tracy, David Watson, and Charles Yancey.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1816 January 16, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 43-45. (Box-folder 1:15)
  Expects no opposition to Mr. Miller's petition. Some resistance to the bill for establishing Central College. Questioning of powers given the professors to imprison students. Possibility of a school for the deaf and dumb, taught by a Mr. Braidwood, to be attached to the college. Recommends enlisting the cooperation of Chapman Johnson, William G. Poindexter, Edward Watts and John W. Green of the Senate. References to [Peter] Carr, [Thomas W.] Maury, and [Charles] Yancey. [1387]
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1816 January 23, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 45-47. (Box-folder 1:16)
  Objections to the Central College bill. Papers in Captain Miller's case with respect to the Reed estate. Copy of the bill to prevent obstructions in the navigable watercourses of Virginia. Appropriations for Literary Fund and for endowment of a professorship for teaching the deaf and dumb. Dr. Smith asks recommendation of a textbook on the principles of government for use at William and Mary. References to Chapman Johnson, John Locke, Jean Jacques Rousseau, Jean Baptiste Say, and Charles Yancey.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1816 January 24, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 50-51; B of R VI 58 (MS. in DLC); Adams II 66-67. (Box-folder 1:17)
  Requests permission to publish T. J.'s letter to Peter Carr regarding the establishment of Central College. Possible locations: Charlottesville, Staunton, or Lexington. Move to shift seat of government to Staunton. References to [Charles F.] Mercer.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson. 1816 February 14, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 56. (Box-folder 1:18)
  Passage of bill for Central College, Mr. Miller's bill, and the bill respecting navigable waters. Reference to [John W.] Green.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1816 February 21, ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 57-60. (Box-folder 1:19)
  Passage of Captain Miller's bill and of bill respecting navigable water; rejection of lottery bill to purchase Triplett Estis' property. Possible appropriation of U. S. surplus to Literary Fund. Modifications in Central College Bill respecting powers of college proctor, glebe lands, and the Literary Fund. Translation of Jean Baptiste Say's Traité d'economie politique. Mentions William Cabell, John W. Green, Chapman Johnson, Thomas W. Maury, and Wilson C. Nicholas.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1816 February 26, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 60-61. (Box-folder 1:20)
  Publication of T. J.'s letter to Peter Carr. Appropriation of Virginia's U. S. Government stock to education. Presbyterians in Lexington and Scotch-Irish in Staunton will object to Albemarle as site for university since they hope to move seat of government to Staunton. Washington College at Lexington the bantling of the Federalists. Trouble with Colonel Monroe about caucus for an electoral ticket. References to Wilson C. Nicholas and [Charles F.] Mercer.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Warminster, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1816 July 4, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 62-65. (Box-folder 1:21)
  Maine's method of preparing hawthorne hedges is best. References to James Henderson, Isaac Newton, Dobson's Encyclopedia, and Lord Karmes' translation of Say's Traité d'economie politique. Implementation of General Assembly act requiring an accurate map of each county.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1816 August 4, ALS. 4 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Partly printed: Cabell 6769. (Box-folder 1:22)
  Superiority of thorn hedges. Surveying for the map authorized by the Assembly (Herman Boye's A Map of the State of Virginia). Advisability of a convention to amend the Virginia Constitution, favored by westerners desiring to place the pecuniary burdens of government on the easterners and by Federalist bank stockholders wishing to charter fifteen banks. Books by Montesquieu, Destutt de Tracy, and Say as textbooks at William and Mary. References to Philip Doddridge, Mr. Meriwether, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., and John Augustine Smith.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 January 12, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 71-73. (Box-folder 1:23)
  Cabell to oppose the petition to which T. J. is opposed, and attend to Count Barziza's petition. Translation of Say's Traité d'economie politique. Copy of a banking bill enclosed. Failure to increase the Literary Fund as recommended by the governor. Col. [Samuel?] Taylor author of petition from Port Royal. Appointment of Cabell as a Visitor of Central College. Difficulty in obtaining money for colleges. Possible site for the University in Staunton. References to Thomas W. Maury.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 February 9, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 73-74. (Box-folder 1:24)
  Rejection of Count Barziza's petition. Is attending to Turnpike Bill. Hewing down of mammoth bank bill. References to Thomas W. Maury, [Joseph] Milligan (bookseller), William C. Rives, Tracy's Political Economy, and Archibald Thweatt.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 February 19, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Partly printed: Cabell 74. (Box-folder 1:25)
  Report on Turnpike Bill, bill to call a convention, bill to equalize senatorial districts (modeled after bill reported by T. J., Pendleton, and Wythe in 1779), and the University Bill. Mentions Archibald Thweatt and Charles Yancey.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 March 30, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 75. (Box-folder 1:26)
  Sends Maine's recipe for preparation of haws found in Brown's Rural Affairs.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Bremo, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 April 23, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 75-76. (Box-folder 1:27)
  Inability to attend meeting of the Board of Visitors of Central College. References to Bedford and Goochland counties, Enniscorthy, John Hartwell Cocke, James Madison, and David Watson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 August 18, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 76-78. (Box-folder 1:28)
  Catalog of English books sold by Barrois at Paris. Subscriptions to Central College from Albemarle, Amherst, Campbell, Lancaster, Northumberland, Richmond, and Westmoreland counties. Death of Cabell's mother. Comments of T. J.'s manuscript on meteorological subjects. References to William Brent, George Cabell, John Camm, Hill Carter, Sterling Claiborne, Ellyson Currie, Thomas Eubanks, David S. Garland, Spottswood Garland, William J. Lewis, James Madison, Roderick McCullock, William Pope, Robert Rives, Mr. Ritchie, Henry St. George Tucker, Robert Walker, and Edmund Winston.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Charlottesville, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 October 7, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 81. (Box-folder 1:29)
  Delay in arriving at Board of Visitors meeting due to the meeting of the Association for an Agricultural Society. References to John Hartwell Cocke, James Madison, James Monroe, Judge [Archibald?] Stewart, and David Watson.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Edgewood, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 October 14, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 82-83. (Box-folder 1:30)
  Plan for schools and colleges throughout the state of Virginia. Copy of membership list of Cincinnati left at Monticello. John Wayles Eppes endeavoring to secure subscribers at Buckingham Court House. Advises delay on the report to the Agricultural Society. Mentions John Hartwell Cocke, Thomas Mann Randolph, Jr., and Arthur Young's Annals.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 December 3, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Partly printed: Cabell 85-87. (Box-folder 1:31)
  Subscriptions to Central College from [Henry St. George?] Tucker and John Coalter. Plan for primary schools throughout the state. Opposition to Central College from Federalists, bigots, members of the Society of Cincinnati, and from friends of Washington College at Lexington. William and Mary people are liberal. References to Judge Brooke, John W. Green, Armistead Holmes, Chapman Johnson, and Edward Watts.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Robert G. Scott, Chairman of the Committee of Schools and Colleges. 1817 December 13, ALS. Draft. 5 pp. Endorsed by T. J. [Copy sent to T. J.]. #2791-a. Enclosed in [1511]. Printed: Cabell 94-96. (Box-folder 1:32)
  Jefferson's ideas regarding the bill providing for the establishment of primary schools, academies, colleges, and a university. Discussion of whether education should be compulsory.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1817 December 29, ALS. 6 pp. Endorsed by T. J. #2791-a. Printed: Cabell 89-94. (Box-folder 1:33)
  Opposition by members of the Society of Cincinnati to Central College, preferring to give funds to Washington College. Presbyterians oppose because T. J. is an infidel. Opposition in the Assembly to setting up a system of public education in Virginia. Encloses copy of letter sent to Robert Scott, Chairman of Committee for Schools and Colleges [1504]. Site for the University. Report on the Literary Fund. References to Francis T. Brooke, William Cabell, John Coalter, Thomas Cooper, Mr. Garrett, Chapman Johnson, Wilson C. Nicholas, [Alfred H.?] Powell, Spencer Roane, Henry Tucker, and Edward Watts.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 January 5, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Enclosure: C. Tompkins, ALS. 2 pp. Partly printed: Cabell 99-101. (Box-folder 1:34)
  Encloses letter from Major Christopher Tompkins regarding the price of bricklaying for Central College. Essay in the Enquirer by Mr. Giles. Prospects not good for the general education bill. Receipt of the papers of Poinsot des Essarts. Information regarding subscriptions to Central College from William Brent, Mr. Currie, and Creed Taylor. References to Wilson C. Nicholas, James P. Preston, Mr. Brown (bricklayer), and Mr. Night (bricklayer).
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 January 22, ALS. 3 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Enclosure: Creed Taylor ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by Cabell. Partly printed: Cabell 108-110. (Box-folder 1:35)
  Search regarding land will be carried out for T. J. in the Register's Office. Copy of the Report of the Visitors circulated in the Assembly. Copy of T. J.'s letters regarding primary schools given to Robert Scott, Chairman of the Committee on Schools and Colleges. Motion to move the capital. Opposition to Central College by the Washington College people. Recommends that William Brent, John T. Brooke, John Hartwell Cocke, and George Poindexter run for the Assembly. Bank loan being negotiated. Recommends annuity from the Literary Fund as best income for Central College. Encloses note from Chancellor Creed Taylor regarding T. J.'s proposed system of public education. References to Jesse W. Garth, James Madison, Robert Mallory, Dabney Minor, and James Monroe.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 January 23, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 111. (Box-folder 1:36)
  Disappointment in the bill reported by the Committee of Schools and Colleges. Visitors will be personally responsible for a bank loan to Central College. Movement of seat of government from Richmond to the West postponed.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to John Brockenbrough. 1818 January 30, ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. [Copy sent by Cabell to T. J.] Printed: Cabell 114-115. (Box-folder 1:37)
  To the President of the Bank of Virginia, covering reports by the Visitors of Central College, given to enable the bank to judge the merits of a loan sought in anticipation of subscriptions.
- John Brockenbrough, Richmond, to Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond. 1818 January 31, ALS. 1 pp. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Deposited by Philip B. Campbell. Printed: Cabell 115-116. (Box-folder 1:38)
  Agreeing to lend money to Central College for 60 days with renewal of notes possible. Originally enclosed in Cabell to Jefferson, 1818 February 1.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 1, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 112-113. (Box-folder 1:39)
  Fears failure of general education bill for Virginia. Requests T. J. to draw bill for annuity from Literary Fund for endowment of professorships. Inquires with regard to Des Essarts' land patents. References to Robert Scott, Samuel Taylor, and [George J.] Davison.
- Joseph Carrington Cabell, Richmond, to Thomas Jefferson, Monticello. 1818 February 1, ALS. 2 pp. Endorsed by T. J. Photocopy. #2791. Original in Papers of Thomas Jefferson. Printed: Cabell 113-114. (Box-folder 1:40)